<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: octopress | Things To Think About]]></title>
  <link href="http://agnanachandran.github.io/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://agnanachandran.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-17T14:11:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://agnanachandran.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Anojh Gnanachandran]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[anojhgnanachandran@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to do X in Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://agnanachandran.github.io/blog/2013/12/20/how-to-do-x-in-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-20T23:11:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://agnanachandran.github.io/blog/2013/12/20/how-to-do-x-in-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So I spent the last couple days tweaking my Octopress themes and relearning how to do things since not blogging for a while and getting a new MBP. Navigating the Octopress file hierarchy isn&rsquo;t easy, but hopefully this post will help you (and be a useful reference for myself).</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So, let&rsquo;s start with a preview of what we have to work with. If you&rsquo;re reading this, I assume you know a bit about Git, the Unix shell, and what Octopress is.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the file hierarchy, my current setup, and the Git configuration.</p>

<h3>My current setup:</h3>

<p>For starters, I&rsquo;m using [oh-my] zsh with the popular <u>Solarized</u> colour scheme. A typical Octopress folder looks something like this:</p>

<p>``` bash
$ tree octopress -LF 1
octopress
├── CHANGELOG.markdown
├── Gemfile
├── Gemfile.lock
├── README.markdown
├── README.md
├── Rakefile
├── <em>config.yml
├── </em>deploy/
├── config.rb
├── config.ru
├── plugins/
├── public/
├── sass/
└── source/</p>

<p>5 directories, 9 files
```</p>

<p>A typical Octopress configuration uses two branches (master and source). I use GitHub Pages for deployment and it looks for files in the master branch. But while editing posts and stylesheets, we really only have to worry about the source branch.</p>

<h3>Top-level Configuration</h3>

<p>_config.yml holds various top-level/administrative info for your blog. This is where you&rsquo;d put your blog&rsquo;s name, your Disqus shortname (if applicable), what links you want in your navigation bar, usernames for various services (GitHub, Facebook, G+, etc.), Google analytics tracking ID, and so on.</p>

<h3>Rake Tasks</h3>

<p>A quick primer for non-ruby enthusiasts:
<code>rake</code> is basically the Ruby version of <code>GNU make</code>. Some of the useful rake tasks descriptions are below. Upon executing any of the below rake tasks, a number of useful commands will be run resulting in some otherwise complex thing being completed.</p>

<p><strong>clean</strong>                     &mdash; clean out caches: .pygments-cache, .gist-cache, .sass-cache</p>

<p><strong>deploy</strong>                    &mdash; default deploy task</p>

<p><strong>gen_deploy</strong>                &mdash; generate website and deploy</p>

<p><strong>generate</strong>                  &mdash; generate jekyll site</p>

<p><strong>install[theme]</strong>            &mdash; initial setup for octopress: copies the default theme into the path of jekyll&rsquo;s generator.</p>

<p><strong>list</strong>                      &mdash; list tasks</p>

<p><strong>new_post[title]</strong>           &mdash; begin a new post in source/_posts</p>

<p><strong>preview</strong>                   &mdash; preview the site in a web browser</p>

<p><strong>watch</strong>                     &mdash; watch the site and regenerate when it changes</p>

<h3>Writing a new post</h3>

<p><code>bash
$ rake new_post['New post title with Punctuation!']
</code></p>

<p>creates a Markdown file in <code>source/_posts</code> named &ldquo;2013-12-28-new-post-title-with-punctuation.markdown&rdquo;, for example.</p>

<p>Deleting the file effectively deletes the post (assuming you haven&rsquo;t already published the post to the interwebs)</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;d like to preview your post in the browser,</p>

<p><code>bash
$ rake preview
</code></p>

<p>will do the trick and show you your blog at localhost:4000 (<a href="http://whatismyipaddress.com/localhost">more info on localhost</a>). HTTP requests and responses will be logged in the same terminal window, so I recommend opening a seperate tab/window specifically for running this process.</p>

<p>Upon saving the file and refreshing the browser window, you&rsquo;ll see how your post (along with the rest of the blog) will look.</p>

<p>Lastly, saving your post&rsquo;s progress (anything done in the source branch really), can be done through</p>

<p><code>bash
$ git add .
$ git commit -m 'Your helpful message goes here'
$ git push origin source
</code></p>

<h3>Changing themes</h3>

<p><code>bash
$ cd octopress
$ git clone GIT_URL .themes/THEME_NAME
$ rake install['THEME_NAME']
$ rake generate
</code></p>

<p>A number of themes are available <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/wiki/3rd-Party-Octopress-Themes">here</a>. I&rsquo;ve opted for the <a href="https://github.com/mikeclarke/villainy-octopress-theme">&ldquo;villainy&rdquo;</a> theme with several personal customizations. I&rsquo;ll detail how I did those changes below.</p>

<h3>Make your blog feel like home</h3>

<p>Disclaimer: If you&rsquo;re anything like me, you may spend several hours tweaking the various SCSS, HTML, and JS files at your disposal. It&rsquo;s pretty addicting.</p>

<p>A little trick I use when I want to find where a specific css selector&rsquo;s attributes are defined is to use <code>fgrep</code>. For example, running</p>

<p>``` bash
$ cd sass
$ fgrep -r &lsquo;meta&rsquo; *</p>

<h1>For long results, pipe to &lsquo;less&rsquo; if desired</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>finds me the exact SASS file(s) I need (and any duplicate declarations that need to be eliminated).</p>

<p>A more detailed description can be found <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/theme/">here</a>.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for now folks; if there&rsquo;s anything you&rsquo;d like me to add, shoot me an <a href="mailto:anojhgnanachandran@gmail.com">email</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
